Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm
1932-1971
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Southern Tenant Farmers' Union
Microfilming Corporation of America
5204 mf
6.67 cubic feet
60 microfilm reels
Microfilm, interviews, autobiographies, photographs, sermons, speeches (documents), oral histories (document genres), microfilm, records.
Consist of correspondence, reports, ledgers, legal documents, leaflets, printed material, photographs, and newspapers published by the union. These document the activities of the Southern Tenant Farmers' Union from its origins through its transformations into the National Farm Labor Union in 1946 and the National Agriculture Workers Union in 1952, and through its merger with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters Union in 1960. The records also contain selected materials from the Socialist Party Archives at Duke University and from the Howard A. Kester papers, which document the earliest years of the Southern Tenant Farmers' Union. The last sixteen reels document H.L. Mitchell's activities as president of Local 300 of the Allied and Agricultural Workers Union.
8433769
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 21, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Southern Tenant Farmers' Union (STFU), a biracial union of sharecroppers, tenant farmers, and small landowners, came into existence in the cotton plantation country of Arkansas in July, 1934, under the leadership of a group of socialists, including H.L. Mitchell and Howard Kester. Although locals were soon established in Missouri, Oklahoma, Texas, Mississippi, and Alabama, the union's base of operation remained in Arkansas until 1945.
Farm mechanization and the impact of World War II shifted the union's focus from tenant farmers to migrant farm workers, whose numbers were rapidly increasing. The union also began supplying temporary cannery workers during the 1940's.
From 1937 to 1939, the STFU was affiliated with the CIO through the United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America (UCAPAWA). After the STFU's withdrawal from the CIO in response to ideological differences with the UCAPAWA, it remained independent until it secured direct affiliation with the A.F. of L. in 1946. At that time, the organization's name changed to the National Farm Labor Union (NFLU) and organizing efforts shifted to farm workers in California. During the 1950's, the NFLU's successor, the National Agricultural Workers' Union (NAWU), focused on organizing sugar, rice, and strawberry workers in Louisiana.
In 1960, the NAWU surrendered its AFL-CIO charter and merged with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen. H.L. Mitchell, former secretary of the SFTU, headed Local 300 of the Allied and Agricultural Workers' Union, organizing rice mill workers and fishermen in Louisiana.
Scope and Contents
Consist of correspondence, reports, ledgers, legal documents, leaflets, printed material, photographs, and newspapers published by the union. These document the activities of the Southern Tenant Farmers' Union from its origins through its transformations into the National Farm Labor Union in 1946 and the National Agriculture Workers Union in 1952, and through its merger with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters Union in 1960. The records also contain selected materials from the Socialist Party Archives at Duke University and from the Howard A. Kester papers, which document the earliest years of the Southern Tenant Farmers' Union. The last sixteen reels document H.L. Mitchell's activities as president of Local 300 of the Allied and Agricultural Workers Union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5204: Southern Tenant Farmers Union Speeches and Interviews 5859: Southern Tenant Farmers Union Research Files 5859 P: Southern Tenant Farmers Union Photographs 6252 MB: Brian McNeill Collection of Southern Tenant Farmers Union Memorabilia
African American agricultural laborers -- Southern States; African Americans -- Employment -- Southern States; Church and labor -- United States; Farm tenancy -- Southern States; Migrant agricultural laborers -- United States; Migrant labor--United States.; Sharecropping.; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- Southern States; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- United States; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- California; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- Louisiana; Cannery workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Fishers -- Labor unions -- Louisiana; Burgess, David S., 1917-; Gibbins, Thomas H., 1897-; Johnson, Clyde, 1908-; Mitchell, H. L. (Harry Leland), 1906-; Alabama Share Croppers' Union; Allied and Agricultural Workers Union. Local 300 (La.); Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America; American Newspaper Guild; Louisiana Farmers' Union; Microfilming Corporation of America; National Farm Labor Union (U.S.); Oil Workers International Union; Share Croppers Union; Socialist Party (U.S.); United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 550 (Oakland, Calif.); United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing, and Allied Workers of America; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Local 610 (Pittsburgh, Pa.); National Agricultural Workers Union; National Farm Labor Union (U.S.); Kester, Howard, 1904-
8433769
- 1934; January, 1935 to February 1936 (Reel 1)
  - 1934, 1 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Only two folders of papers survive from this year. There is a copy of the union's first Constitution, as well as the Constitution of the Oklahoma Renters Union upon which the STFU document was based. The papers include a report by Mitchell on the union's activities during 1934, an STFU "Program of Action", and The Plight of the Sharecropper, a booklet by Norman Thomas (note: this is the original edition. A copy of the revised edition appears in the selection from the Howard A. Kester Papers on Reel 59). There are a few pieces of correspondence with the AAA and with Donald Henderson of the National Conference of Agricultural, Lumber and Rural Workers.
  - January to April, 1935, 2 (Reel 1)
    The main topics in the papers for this period include the Norcross Plantation eviction case, the arrest of STFU speaker Ward H. Rodgers in Marked Tree, Arkansas during a union meeting, and the STFU delegation sent to Washington in April to picket the Department of Agriculture. There are a number of statements, press releases, and letters related to the Rodgers case. There is also a great deal of correspondence from Norman Thomas; see especially his exchange with Secretary of Agriculture Henry A. Wallace (April 16). Readers interested in the union's activities during 1935 should consult the selection from the Howard A. Kester Papers on Reel 59 for additional materials.
  - May to September, 1935, 3 (Reel 1)
    Correspondence during may Concerns the Controversy within the AAA over Section 7a of the Cotton Contract; see especially a letter from Norman Thomas describing his recent conversation with President Roosevelt on this subject (May 8). There is an exchange of letters with union lawyer CT Carpenter and the ACLU on the advisability of further legal action against Arkansas planters to counter eviction of tenants. The STFU experienced troubles within the ranks of its own leadership and was forced to expel both WH Stultz and J.O. Green. On the expulsions, see the injunction obtained against Stultz (June 17), an affidavit sworn by Stultz affirming his dire poverty (June 27) and the Constitution of Green's Fascist-style "Tenant Farmers' and Labors' Patriotic Union" (July 19). There is also an interesting communication from the Alabama Share Croppers Union on Green's attempt to subvert their strike. The papers for September include press releases, leaflets, etc. relating to the strike of cotton pickers called by the union in eastern Arkansas.
  - October to December, 1935, 4 (Reel 1)
    There is correspondence relating to Howard Kester's successful attempt to secure an endorsement of the STFU at the AF of L annual convention, including a copy of the resolution adopted (Oct 17). Items of special interest include a series of reports from J.R. Butler on his organizing trip to Texas (Oct. 26 to 31), a memorandum by Mitchell entitled "A New Homestead Law" (Nov 20), a circular sent out by Kester soliciting support for The Sharecropper's Voice (Dec. 10) and replies, and a report by Butler on an anti-poll tax meeting in Little Rock (Dec 10).
  - No Date, 1935, 5 (Reel 1)
    Reports from organizers Robert Reed and N.W. Webb; materials on the cotton pickers' strike of September, including Kester's report entitled "Acts of Tyranny and Terror"; a compendium of individual acts of violence against union members; the STFU brief before the Arkansas Supreme Court in the Norcross Plantation eviction case; plans for rehabilitating evicted tenants; circular letter issued by the Conference of Younger Churchmen of the South to protest the arrest of Ward H. Rodgers; instruction sheets for STFU organizers and locals; report on the Share Croppers Union (Ala.); report on the STFU delegation sent to Washington to picket the AAA; a brief history of the STFU.
  - January, 1936, 6 (Reel 1)
    The Second Annual STFU Convention was held at Little Rock on January 3 to 5; the papers include the program, press releases, the "report of the Second Annual Convention," the Report of the Executive Secretary for 1935; and "Ceremony of the Land" by Howard Kester. There is a good deal of material concerning the union's attempt to gain representation at a conference called by Secretary of Agriculture Henry A. Wallace on the future of the AAA (Jan. 8 to 15). Another major topic is the situation at Parkin, Arkansas, where a mass eviction of tenants at the C.H. Dibble plantation was followed by the violent disruption of a union meeting in the adjacent town of Earle and the erection of a tent colony to shelter the homeless families. Lastly, there is much correspondence with women STFU members on the decision by the convention to create separate locals for women.
  - February, 1936, 7 (Reel 1)
    Union activity during February was devoted to obtaining help for evicted tenants from various New Deal agencies. See especially Gardner Jackson's report on his discussions with the WPA (12) and Kester's letters on his negotiations with the Resettlement Administration concerning a projected cooperative farm for displaced tenants (18, 21, 29). Toward the end of the month, a frequent topic in the correspondence is the case of Jim Ball, a black STFU organizer convicted of "intent to kill" a deputy sheriff during the violence at Earle in January; see especially the STFU brief before the Arkansas Supreme Court appealing Ball's case (26).
- March 1936 to August 1936. (Reel 2)
  - March, 1936, 1 (Reel 2)
    There is an interesting exchange of correspondence between Kester and Mitchell on the desirability of setting up an STFU-sponsored cooperative farm to house evicted tenants (13,18,23), as well as a report from Kester on a conference called by Gardner Jackson's National Committee on Rural Social Planning (31). Other items of special interest include Kester's pamphlet, Revolt of the Sharecroppers (17), Mitchell's preliminary instructions to his locals on a forthcoming strike (9,19), and Mitchell's widespread appeals for financial help for the union, including letters to two of his friends in New Orleans explaining in detail the philosophy of the STFU (23).
  - April, 1936, 2 (Reel 2)
    There is a flood of telegrams from Gardner Jackson through the first half of the month relating to the presentation of evidence of anti-union violence before the Senate Committee on Civil Liberties chaired by Robert M. La Follette, Jr. The papers also include a frequent exchange of letters between Mitchell and STFU Vice-President E.B. McKinney on McKinney's fund-raising trip to New York and on his complaints of mistreatment by his fellow STFU officers. There is a mimeographed letter from Mitchell to all locals on strike preparations (18) and a letter from Mitchell to Norman Thomas on reports that Donald Henderson was attempting to undermine the STFU leadership (27).
  - May, 1936, 3 (Reel 2)
    The strike, which began May 18, dominates the union correspondence for this month. See especially the frequent STFU press releases on the strike, the circular letter sent out to AF of L affiliates appealing for strike funds (21), and Mitchell's almost daily communications with Gardner Jackson. Toward the end of May, a major issue developed in the case of Paul Peacher, a Crittenden County (Ark.) Deputy Sheriff accused of holding sharecroppers in peonage on his penal farm; see especially the union press release, "Concentration Camps in Arkansas" (21).
  - June, 1936, 4 (Reel 2)
    The strike and the violence mounted by the planters to break the strike are the main issues in the papers for June. The papers include several STFU press releases on the strike and a considerable amount of correspondence between Mitchell and union members on the expenditure of strike relief funds. Friends of the union also sent STFU headquarters copies of their letters to state and Federal officials protesting the unchecked violence. There is also a discussion of plans to send a sharecropper delegation to picket Franklin D. Roosevelt on his visit to Little Rock (3 to 10). On the problems of raising funds for legal defense, see especially two letters from Professor William R. Amberson (23,37).
  - July, 1936, 5 (Reel 2)
    Several STFU members faced legal charges in the aftermath of the strike, and Gardner Jackson kept union headquarters informed of his efforts to raise bail money (6,10,28). The ACLU sent a copy of their letter to Arkansas governor J.M. Funtrell listing a number of cases in which the civil rights of union members were allegedly violated (8), while J.C. Brookfield, a union lawyer, and the WDL sent reports on the cases of Nathan Smith and Josh Turner, both held on felony charges in Crittenden County (23,30). STFU Vice-President E.B. McKinney, in hiding from the Memphis police, wrote frequently about his poverty and the mistreatment of blacks by white STFU leaders; see also Mitchell's reply (31). Also of special interest in July is a set of three "test letters", addressing black union members by title, sent out in an attempt to catch local postmasters who refused to deliver mail addressed in this fashion (5,7 -- see also an explanatory note by Mitchell at this date).
  - August, 1936, 6 (Reel 2)
    Topics under discussion during August include plans to send former STFU leader Walter Moskop to California after his attempt to assassinate H.L. Mitchell, the forthcoming Socialist Party campaign in Arkansas, a training school for union organizers held at the Delta Cooperative Farm beginning August 17, legal defense problems, and the discussion of STFU tactics toward Governor Futrell's planned Commission on Farm Tenancy. There is a letter from Mitchell to Donald Henderson protesting Henderson's editorial in The Rural Worker (12) and an exchange between Mitchell and Gardner Jackson on whether the STFU should concentrate on building its internal structure or on gaining national publicity (11,12).
- September 1936 to Decembe 1936, and Miscellaneous Union Business, 1936. (Reel 3)
  - September, 1936, 1 (Reel 3)
    Governor Futrell's Commission on Farm Tenancy met at Hot Springs on September 21; see the STFU Statement to the Commission which appears on that date. Other topics in the papers include the speaking tours of Socialist Party candidates Norman Thomas and George A. Nelson, including Thomas' Memphis speech entitled "Arkansas Shame" (17), the STFU claim that WPA officials were dropping workers from the relief rolls in an attempt to drive down Arkansas plantation wages, and arrangements with the Workers Defense League (formerly the Labor and Socialist Defense Committee) to handle STFU legal problems. There are letters from union members A.B. Brookins and J.F. Lee, recounting the violence they have experienced (7).
  - October, 1936, 2 (Reel 3)
    The first half of the month was relatively quiet for the STFU. The union filed a Supplementary Statement to Gov. Futrell's Commission (10), and a similar commission in Oklahoma issued a report of its proceedings (22). Mitchell wrote organizer Roy Morelock to explain the new system of record keeping adopted by the union (13). During the second half of October, two major issues developed: the complaint of organizer L.N. Sybert that white union officials were not fair in their treatment of black members, and the charges made by US District Attorney Fred Isgrig concerning an STFU fund-raising letter sent out by the Workers Defense League in New York (24, 29 to 31). The papers include a letter from Mitchell to the WDL listing the status of the various court cases the union was currently involved in (21); a mimeographed letter from Howard Kester to the union membership explaining the work of the Central Defense Committee and appealing to them for funds (26); an AF of L resolution endorsing the STFU (28); and a "Calendar of Events" describing the battles of the STFU from the strike of May 18 through the Isgrig incident in October (n.d.[October]).
  - November, 1936, 3 (Reel 3)
    There is considerable correspondence concerning the Isgrig statement during the first half of the month, including a copy of a letter from Isgrig to Aron S. Gilmartin, head of the WDL (3). Other items of interest include: a letter from Mitchell to Norman Thomas, describing his recent meeting in Tampa, Florida, with Gardner Jackson and Donald Henderson in an attempt to iron out the differences between Henderson and the STFU (17); a report from Ward Rodgers on a lettuce workers strike in the Salinas Valley, Calif. (8); an open letter to President Roosevelt from the STFU (20); and three letters from Rev. Claude Williams on his proposal to start a training school for STFU organizers (19,23,26). Although Deputy Sheriff Paul D. Peacher was convicted of peonage during the last week of November, there is little in the papers relating to the case, except for a congratulatory note from Norman Thomas (25).
  - December, 1936, 4 (Reel 3)
    The papers for this month are primarily concerned with preparations for events scheduled to take place in January, including the STFU Annual Convention held at Muskogee, Okla., on Jan. 14 to 17, the Southern meeting of the Socialist Party at Norris, Tenn., on Jan. 2 and 3, and the public hearings of the President's Special Commission on Farm Tenancy, held at Dallas, Texas, and Montgomery, Alabama, on Jan. 4 and 6, respectively. At the beginning of December, the Workers Defense League sent Aaron Levenstein to STFU headquarters in Memphis to help with legal defense and fund-raising. Levenstein's almost daily correspondence with Sidney Hertzberg in the New York office of WDL provides much information on plans to initiate a National Sharecroppers Week and the "Friends of the STFU". Other items include: a prospectus for an organizers training school set up by Claude Williams at Little Rock on Dec. 13 to 22 (13); a letter of apology from Donald Henderson for his editorial in The Rural Worker (21); and the minutes of the Oklahoma Farm Tenancy Committee (19 and 31).
  - No Date, 1936, 5 (Reel 3)
    Monthly reports from the Edmondson and Post locals; Relief Survey Tabulation, Oklahoma; poem by Robert Lee Eckford, a 10 year old black student; leaflets for strikes and mass meetings; prospectus, "A Suggested Workers' Education Program for East Arkansas"; bill drafted by STFU for the Arkansas legislature proposing the creation of a Bureau of Landlords and Tenants; copies of affidavits by union members describing anti-union violence during the strike; "Table of Cases Involving the STFU" (a listing of major legal cases); STFU briefs filed in the cases of Willie Sue Blagden, J.M. Reese, and Sam Bennett; statements and an affidavit on anti-union violence by Mitchell and Sam Franklin; typescripts of histories of the early years of the union, including two by J.R. Butler; list of all STFU locals; press releases, including one on the Frank Weems case.
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1936, 6 (Reel 3)
    Folder 83 -- Not Filmed. Folder 87 -- Local Secretaries' Reports. Folder 88 -- State and County Secretaries' Reports. Folder 89 -- Strike Ballots. Folder 90 -- Not Filmed.
- January 1937 to June 1937. (Reel 4)
  - January, 1937, 1 (Reel 4)
    The year began with public hearings of the President's Special Commission on Farm Tenancy at Dallas and Montgomery. The papers include the STFU statements at both hearings, as well as memoranda to the commission from Odis Sweeden and Fred Matthews, STFU leaders in Oklahoma and Texas, respectively (4 to 6). Virtually all of the papers near the middle of the month have to do with the Muskogee Convention, including the "Auditors' Preliminary Report to the Convention", the convention program, Howard Kester's "Ceremony of the Land", revised for the Muskogee meeting, the "Proceedings of the Third Annual Convention" (in both printed and typescript form), and telegrams to the convention from many high-placed government and labor officials. Following the convention, there is considerable correspondence concerning a supposed agreement reached at Muskogee between Mitchell and David Fowler, a UMWA official, to cut ties between the STFU and Commonwealth College. See especially a copy of a letter from Claude Williams to Gardner Jackson, vehemently attacking the alleged bargain (23), and two letters from Howard Kester to Roger Baldwin, explaining the problems at the college and Mitchell's actions (8, 28).
  - February, 1937, 2 (Reel 4)
    The Mississippi River overflowed its banks at the beginning of the month, and much of the correspondence concerns flood relief for union members. Following the Muskogee convention, union activity in the Southwest accelerated, and there is a great amount of communication with such leaders as Odis Sweeden and John M. Denney in Oklahoma and Fred Matthews and J.R. Freeland in Texas. Much of the correspondence with Sweeden and Denney concerns the supposed Mitchell-Fowler-Jackson bargain at Muskogee (4,12,15). About the middle of the month, two black union members in Forrest City, Ark. were murdered and the lawyers sent to investigate were run out of town.
  - March, 1937, 3 (Reel 4)
    The first week of March was National Sharecroppers Week, but there is virtually no information about it in the papers. The only other event of importance during this month was a meeting of the National Executive Committee on March 21; see Mitchell's detailed report to the Committee which appears on that date. Other items of interest include a 22-page report from Stephen C. Seys, Secretary of the Jasper (Ark.) local (18), an STFU press release on the AAA statement concerning planter violations of the cotton control program (20), and a pamphlet entitled "Legislative Program of the STFU of Oklahoma" (1).
  - April, 1937, 4 (Reel 4)